Guide to the Office of the Chancellor records, 1969-1988 UA.06.01.0001
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Office of the Chancellor records
1969-1988
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Duke University. Office of the Chancellor
UA.06.01.0001
7.5 Linear Feet
The Chancellor of Duke University was a position under the President, designed to exercise all of the President's duties when delegated by the President if the President was incapacitated or absent from the position. The last active Chancellor was William Anlyan, whose time as Chancellor spanned from 1988 to 1995. After his tenure, the position is apparently no longer in use. The collection includes files from a variety of different committees and councils related to the administration of Duke University. Collection also includes personal correspondence from members of the Board of Trustees, materials related to planning for the construction of Duke Hospital North, files on a proposed rapid transit system, debt and operating reports, correspondence, and materials related to Duke University's affirmative action and equal employment opportunity policies and programs.
Access Restrictions
Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
Provenance
Transfer
Historical Note
President Emeritus R. L. Flowers was given the title of Chancellor in 1949 and the position was seemingly an honorary one. There are no records of his tenure. The office was re-established in March 1969, when President Douglas M. Knight wanted an officer to assist with an increasing executive workload. The Chancellor was given responsibility for the internal operation of the University. The last active Chancellor in this role was Keith H. Brodie, whose time as Chancellor spanned from 1982 to 1985. In 1987, Dr. William Anlyan was appointed Chancellor, effective July 1988, with a role more focused on representing the University to local, state, national, and international groups and organizations, as well as fundraising for the Capital Campaign.
The Chancellor of Duke University was a position under the President, designed to exercise all of the President's duties when delegated by the President if the President was incapacitated or absent from the position. The Chancellor must have received authorization from the Board of Trustees or the President before assuming these duties.
The Office of the Chancellor worked closely with the Duke University Board of Trustees. The Board of Trustees is the administrative decision-making body that oversees the planning and direction of the University. The Board consists of 36 members. More information about the Board can be found at the University Secretary's website at: https://trustees.duke.edu/
Under the University By-laws of May 10, 1988, the Chancellor is an executive officer with powers and duties assigned by the President. The occupants of the office have been the following: Robert L. Flowers (1949-1951), Barnes Woodhall (1969-1970, pro tem), A. Kenneth Pye (1970-1971), John O. Blackburn (1971-1976); A. Kenneth Pye (1976-1982), Keith H. Brodie (1982-1985), and William G. Anlyan (1988-1995).
Collection Overview
The collection includes files from a variety of different committees and councils related to the administration of Duke University. Committees are related to student housing, residential life, the environment, traffic, equal employment, affirmative action, physical education, athletics, business and finance, and religious life.
Includes personal correspondence from various members of the Board of Trustees. The collection also includes materials related to planning for the construction of Duke Hospital North, files on a proposed rapid transit system, debt and operating reports, correspondence, and materials related to Duke University's affirmative action and equal employment opportunity policies and programs.
Related Materials
A. Kenneth Pye, Chancellor, records and papers, 1960-1983. (University Archives, Duke University.)
Preliminary Guide to the H. Keith H. Brodie, Chancellor, records, 1970-1985 (University Archives, Duke University.)
John O. Blackburn, Chancellor, Records, 1971-1976. (University Archives, Duke University.)
Equal Employment Opportunity Committee records, 1969-1973. (University Archives, Duke University.)
Office for Institutional Equity records, 1962-ongoing. (University Archives, Duke University.)
Discrimination in employment -- North Carolina -- Durham; Affirmative action programs -- North Carolina -- Durham; Duke University. Medical Center; Brodie, H. Keith H. (Harlow Keith Hammond), 1939-; Duke University. Board of Trustees; Duke University -- Administration; Duke University. Equal Employment Opportunity Office; Duke University. Equal Employment Opportunity Committee.
- Committee files, 1969 - 1982; undated
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes files from a variety of different committees and councils related to the administration of Duke University. Committees are related to student housing, residential life, the environment, traffic, equal employment, affirmative action, physical education, athletics, business and finance, religious life, and other subjects.
  Access Restrictions
  Records of the University's Board of Trustees which have been in existence for at least fifty years are available for scholarly research with the permission of the University Archivist. Access to records which have been in existence for less than fifty years shall be granted only by special permission, in writing, from the Board of Trustees.
  - Memoranda, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Advisory Group -- Affirmate Action Goals, 1976 (Box 1)
  - Archives Advisory Committee, 1972-1978 (Box 1)
  - Artists Series Committee, 1969-1970 (Box 1)
  - Athletic Council, 1973-1976 (Box 1)
  - Black Studies Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Chapel Renovation Committee, 1973-1978 (Box 1)
  - University Chaplain -- Search Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Educational Administration, 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Committee on Faculty and Staff Housing [Homesites], 1969-1971 (Box 1)
  - Committee on the Organization of the Graduate Faculty, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Committee on the Use of University Facilities, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Conflict of Interest Committee, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Dean of Trinity College -- Search Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Drama Planning Committee, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Environmental Concerns Committee (DUECC) --Minutes, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Environmental Concerns Committee (DUECC) -- Minutes, 1974-1976; undated (Box 1)
  - Duke University Environmental Concerns Committee (DUECC) -- Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1974-1976 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Traffic Commission, 1970-1972 (Box 1)
  - Duke University -- Traffic Commission, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Duke University -- Traffic Commission, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - Duke University -- Traffic Commission (Parking), 1972 (Box 1)
  - Duke University -- Traffic Commission (Parking), 2, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Duke University Traffic Commission (Parking), 3, 1970-1975 (Box 1)
  - Educational Administration Advisory Group, 1969-1972 (Box 1)
  - Equal Opportunity Committee, 1975-1977 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Benefits Committee, 1969-1978 (Box 1)
  - Faculty Committee on Student Concerns, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Graduate Life Committee [Graduate Resident Life Committee], 1972 (Box 1)
  - Judicial Board, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Judicial Board, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Judicial Board, 1969-1977 (Box 1)
  - Judicial Review Committee, 1973-1975 (Box 1)
  - Officer Education Committee, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Residential Life Committee, Study of Student Residential Life, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Conduct of U.S. Physical Education Programs (Box 1)
    Folder missing February 2021.
  - Residential Life Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Residential Life Committee, 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Residential Life Evaluation Committee, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Safety Commission -- Medical Center, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Safety Committee, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Staff Appeals Committee, 1975 (Box 1)
  - The Good Ship, C.B., undated (Box 1)
  - Student Activities Building Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
  - Task Force Committee on Student Financial Aid Reporting System, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Task Force on Academic Space Utilization Report, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Task Force on Year-Round Operation, Preliminary Report, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Task Force on Campus Christian Ministry, 1972 (Box 1)
  - Task Force on Year-Round Operation, Final Report, Year-Round Education at Duke, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Task Force on Year-Round Operation, Final Report, Year-Round Education at Duke, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Special Task Force to Study the Year-Round Operation of University -- History and Background, 1965-1980 (Box 2)
  - Special Task Force to Study the Year-Round Operation of University -- Subcommittee Reports, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Special Task Force on Year-Round Operation, Final Report, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Special Task Force on Year-Round Operation, Final Report, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Special Task Force on Year of Year-Round Operation of the University -- Surveys (Faculty and Students), 1980 (Box 2)
  - Traffic Appeals Committee, 1973-1976 (Box 2)
  - Traffic Commission -- Medical Center, 1973-1975 (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Faculty Council on Admissions and Financial Aid (UFACS), 1972 (Box 2)
  - Undergraduate Judicial Board, 1970-1972 (Box 2)
  - Unfair Employment Practices Committee (Placement and Services), 1970 (Box 2)
  - University Governance Committee [Commission on University Governance], 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - Vice Provost and Dean search committee, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Ad Hoc Committee on Student Affairs, 1980-1982 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Buildings and Grounds Committee, 1976-1982 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Buildings and Grounds Committee, 1976-1981 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Business and Finance Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Business and Finance Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Business and Finance Committee, 1977-1980 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Business and Finance Committee, 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Duke University Council on Religious Life, 1979-1981 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Trustee Ad Hoc Committee on Compensation, 1980 (Box 2)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2030.
  - Committees -- Trustee Committee for Institutional Advancement, 1969-1978 (Box 2)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2028.
  - Committees -- Trustee Committee on Athletics, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Trustee Committee on Athletics, 1978-1980 (Box 2)
  - Committees -- Trustee Committee on Athletics, 1971-1982 (Box 2)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2032.
  - Trustee Committee on Athletics (Reactivated April 1982), 1971-1982 (Box 3)
  - Committees -- Faculty Liaison Committee, 1977-1981 (Box 3)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2031.
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1975 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous, 1970-1981 (Box 3)
- Correspondence, 1969-1980; undated; 2
  Series includes personal correspondence from various members of the Board of Trustees. Series also includes materials related to the business of the Board of Trustees, which may be restricted.
  - George Allen correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2020.
  - Blanche Brian correspondence, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Nancy Hanks correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
  - Alfred M. Hunt correspondence, 1971 (Box 3)
  - Alexander Mahon correspondence, 1977-1980 (Box 3)
  - Raymond D. Nasher correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2021.
  - Thomas L. Perkins correspondence, 1969-1973 (Box 3)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2023.
  - Clifford W. Perry correspondence, 1969-1970 (Box 3)
  - Henry Rauch correspondence, 1969-1978 (Box 3)
  - Mary Semans correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Wright Tisdale correspondence, 1969-1975 (Box 3)
  - W.M. Upchurch, Jr., correspondence, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
  - Charles B. Wade, Jr., correspondence, 1969 (Box 3)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2026.
  - Charles B. Wade, Jr., correspondence, 1969-1976 (Box 1)
  - Brantley Watson correspondence, 1970 (Box 3)
  - General Correspondence, 1969-1980 (Box 3)
- Administrative files, 1964-1980; undated; 3
  Series includes administrative files of the Board of Trustees, which may be restricted. Includes materials related to Board of Trustees candidates, President's reports to the Board, outlines of the Board's powers and duties, and individual correspondence/materials from Board members.
  - Powers, Duties, and Responsibilities, 1979-1980 (Box 3)
  - President's Report to the Trustees, 1954-1957, Schedule of Operations and Investements, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Trustees and Trustee Candidates, 1970-1976 (Box 3)
  - Trustee Candidates, 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Trustees -- Individual Material, 1969-1971 (Box 3)
- Duke Hospital North files, 1969-1980; undated; 4
  Series includes materials related to planning for the construction of Duke Hospital North. Materials include Board of Trustees resolutions and materials, which may be restricted, files on a proposed rapid transit system, debt and operating reports, correspondence, and comparative data from other hospitals.
  - Hospital G-94 North, Academic Council Review, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Hospital G-94 North, Board Resolution, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    Board of Trustees materials. Access restricted until 2025.
  - Hospital G-94 North, Comparative Data, Other Hospitals, 1975 (Box 3)
  - Hospital G-94 North, Comparative Data, Other Hospitals, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Hospital G-94 North, Current Operating Reports, 1975-1978 (Box 3)
  - Hospital G-94 North, Debt Service, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Hospital G-94 North, Equity and Debt, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Hospital G-94 North, Equity and Debt, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Hospital G-94 North, General, 1973-1975 (Box 3)
  - Medical Center, Personalized Rapid Transit Sysytem, 1975 (Box 3)
  - New Hospital, 1971-1975 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence, 1973-1974 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1977 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978; 1 boxes (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1978 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1979 (Box 4)
  - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 4)
- Affirmative Action files, 1972-1980; undated; 5
  Series includes materials related to Duke University's affirmative action and equal employment opportunity policies and programs. Materials include publications and educational materials related to affirmative action, various affirmative action committee files, Association of Research Libraries (ARL) files, and action plans.
  - Educational materials, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Committee of Duke Libraries, 1969-1977 (Box 5)
  - Action Plans and Guidelines, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
  - American Library Association files, 1970-1974 (Box 5)
  - Articles and Bibliographies, 1969-1975 (Box 5)
  - Equal Opportunity Committee files, 1972-1975 (Box 5)
  - Equal Opportunity Committee files, 1972-1975 (Box 5)
  - Equal Opportunity Committee files, 1973-1975 (Box 5)
  - Minority library internship program files, 1974-1976; undated (Box 5)
  - Association of Research Libraries (ARL) files, 1972-1973 (Box 5)
  - Delores Burke meeting files, 1976-1978; undated (Box 5)
  - Subcommittee on Faculty, Academic Policy, and Grievance Policies files, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
  - Appendix C to Affirmative Action Plan, 1973 (Box 5)
  - Affirmative Action Committee, General files, 1972-1978 (Box 5)
  - Master copies, 1973-1976 (Box 5)
  - Library Affirmative Action Committee, 1972-1978 (Box 5)